# SINDHU KIRANMAI ERNALA

Contact

E1566M, CODA Tech Square 756 W Peachtree St NW Atlanta, GA 30308

Email: sernala3@gatech.edu Web: www.sindhuernala.com

RESEARCH INTERESTS Applying machine learning, statistical modeling, and natural language processing methods to digital trace data, to understand how social technologies affect and improve people's health and well-being. Areas: Computational social science, human-centered machine learning, human computer interaction.

**EDUCATION** 

### Doctor of Philosophy, Computer Science

2016 - present

Georgia Institute of Technology

Dissertation title: Person-centered pathways to care: A computational examination of social media for mental health

Advisor: Munmun De Choudhury

Committee: Eric P.S. Baumer, Moira Burke, Elizabeth Mynatt, Diyi Yang

Ph.D. minor area: Public policy

# Bachelor of Technology, Computer Science with Master of Science, Exact Humanities

2011 - 2016

International Institute of Information Technology Hyderabad (IIIT-H), India

Thesis title: Towards Construction of Social Automaton

Awards & Honors

- Facebook Ph.D. Fellowship Finalist (2020)
- $\bullet\,$  Georgia Tech GVU Foley Scholar Finalist (2020)
- Computing Research Association (CRA-W) Grad Cohort for Women Attendee (2019)
- Special recognition for outstanding reviews, CHI (2019)
- Dean's Merit List (top 5% of the class) for Academic Excellence for 2014, 2015 at IIIT-H
- Commendation award for contributions to all round activities and leadership at IIIT-H

EXPERIENCE

# Graduate Research Assistant, Georgia Tech

August 2016 - present

(with Munmun De Choudhury)

Research Intern, Core Data Science, Facebook

May 2020 - August 2020

(with Moira Burke)

External Research Collaborator

August 2019 - May 2020

Pro Unlimited @ Facebook Inc.

Core Data Science Intern, Facebook

May 2019 - August 2019

(with Moira Burke)

Research Intern, Information Science Institute, USC

May 2017 - August 2017

(with Emilio Ferrara)

Research Intern, Xerox Research Center India

May 2015 - August 2015

(in the Distributed and mobile computing group)

Visiting Student Researcher, Insight Center for Data Analytics May 2014 - July 2014 (with Paul Buitelaar)

**Software Developer Intern, Imaginate Software Labs**May 2013 - July 2013
Worked on server-side web application logic and integration to front-end.

#### Publications Refereed Journal Articles

Ernala, S. K., Kashiparekh, K., Bolous, A., Ali, A., Kane, J., Birnbaum, M., De Choudhury, M.. (2020). A Social Media Study on Mental Health Status Transitions Surrounding Psychiatric Hospitalizations. In PACM CSCW.

Birnbaum, M., Wen, H., Van Meter, A., Ernala, S. K., Rizvi, A. F., Arenare, E., Estrin, D., De Choudhury, M., Kane, J. (2020). Identifying Emerging Mental Illness Utilizing Search Engine Activity: A Feasibility Study. In **PLOS ONE.** 

Birnbaum, M.\*, Ernala, S. K.\*, Rizvi, A. F., Arenare, E., Van Meter, A., De Choudhury, M., Kane, J. (2019). Detecting Relapse in Youth with Psychotic Disorders Utilizing Patient-Generated and Patient-Contributed Digital Data from Facebook. In Nature Partner Journal Schizophrenia. npj Schizophrenia. (\* co-first authors)

Saha, K., Torous, J., **Ernala, S. K.**, Rizuto, C., Stafford, A., & De Choudhury, M. (2019). A Computational Study of Mental Health Awareness Campaigns on Social Media. In **Translational Behavioral Medicine**.

Ernala, S. K., Rizvi, A., Birnbaum, M., Kane, J., & De Choudhury, M. (2018). Linguistic Markers Indicating Therapeutic Outcomes of Social Media Disclosures of Schizophrenia. In Proceedings of the 21st ACM Conference on Computer-Supported Cooperative Work and Social Computing. PACM CSCW 2018 Online First.

Birnbaum, M.\*, Ernala, S. K.\*, Rizvi, A., De Choudhury, M. & Kane, J. (2017). A Collaborative Approach to Identifying Social Media Markers of Schizophrenia by Employing Machine Learning and Clinical Appraisals. In Journal of Medical Internet Research (JMIR). (\* equal contribution)

#### Refereed Conference Proceedings

Ernala, S. K., Burke, M., Leavitt, A., Ellison, N.B. (2020). How Well Do People Report Time Spent on Facebook? An Evaluation of Established Survey Questions with Recommendations. In Proceedings of the 2020 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems. CHI 2020.

Saha, K., Ernala, S. K., Dutta, S., Sharma, E., De Choudhury, M. (2019). Understanding Moderation in Online Mental Health Communities. In 22nd International Conference on Human-Computer Interaction. HCII 2020.

Ernala, S. K., Birnbaum, M., Candan, K., Rizvi, A., Sterling, W., Kane, J., & De Choudhury, M. (2019). Methodological Gaps in Predicting Mental Health States from Social Media: Triangulating Diagnostic Signals. In Proceedings of the 2019 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems. CHI 2019.

Ernala, S. K., Labetoulle, T., Bane, F., Birnbaum, M., Rizvi, A., Kane, J., & De Choudhury, M. (2018). Characterizing Audience Engagement and Assessing its Impact on Social Media Disclosures of Mental Illnesses. In Proceedings of the 12th International AAAI Conference on Web

and Social Media. ICWSM 2018.

Sharma, E., Saha, K., **Ernala, S. K.**, Ghoshal, S., & De Choudhury, M. (2017). Analyzing Ideological Discourse on Social Media: A Case Study of the Abortion Debate. In Proceedings of the CSSA's Annual Conference on Computational Social Science. **CSS 2017.** 

Banerjee, J., Raravi, G., Gupta, M., Ernala, S. K., Kunde, S., & Dasgupta, K. (2016). CAPReS: Context Aware Persona Based Recommendation for Shoppers. In AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence. AAAI 2016.

#### Refereed Workshop Papers

- [1] Sapienza, A.\*, Ernala, S. K.\*, Bessi, A., Lerman, K., & Ferrara, E. (2018). DISCOVER: Mining Online Chatter for Emerging Cyber Threats. In Proceedings of the 3rd Workshop on Computational Methods in CyberSafety, Online Harassment and Misinformation at WWW 2018. (\* equal contribution)
- [2] Poddar, S.\*, **Ernala, S. K.\***, & Singh, N. (2016). PACMAN: Psycho and Computational Framework of an Individual. In Proceedings of the Workshop on Emotion and Sentiment Analysis at the 10th International Conference on Language Resources and Evaluation (LREC). (\* co-first authors)
- [3] Poddar, S.\*, **Ernala, S. K.\***, Singh, N., & Samvara, A. (2016). Towards a Ubiquitous Model of an Individual in Social Machines. In Proceedings of the 25th International Conference Companion on World Wide Web. WWW 2016. (\* co-first authors)
- [4] Asooja, K., Ernala, S. K., & Buitelaar, P. (2015). UNLP at the MediaEval 2015 C@merata Task. In MediaEval 2015.
- [5] Asooja, K., Ernala, S. K., & Buitelaar, P. (2014). UNLP at the MediaEval 2014 C@merata Task. In MediaEval 2014.

#### Refereed Presentations/Abstracts

- [1] Ernala, S. K., Rizvi, A., Birnbaum, M., Kane, J., & De Choudhury, M. (2018). Using Social Media to Identify Risk Markers and Predict Relapse in Schizophrenia. Presented at Social Media and Health Workshop at the International Conference on Web and Social Media. ICWSM 2018
- [2] Birnbaum, M., De Choudhury, M., Rizvi, A., Ernala, S. K., Cecchi, G., & Kane, J. (2018). Identifying Psychotic Symptoms and Predicting Relapse through Social Media Data. In International Conference on Early Intervention in Mental Health. IEPA 2018.
- [3] Birnbaum, M., De Choudhury, M., Rizvi, A., **Ernala, S. K.**, & Kane, J. (2018). Identifying Psychotic Symptoms and Predicting Relapse through Social Media Data. In Fourth Meeting on Patient Reported Outcomes and Person Centered Care in Mental Health Symptoms of Mental Disorders: New Research, Treatments, Digital Health, American Association for the Advancement of Science. AAAS.
- [4] Birnbaum, M., Rizvi, A., De Choudhury, M., **Ernala, S. K.**, Cecchi, G., & Kane, J. (2018). Identifying Psychotic Symptoms and Predicting Relapse Through Social Media. Schizophrenia Bulletin, 44(Suppl 1), S100.

#### Workshops Organized

[1] Technology Ecosystems: Rethinking Resources for Mental Health. Held at CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems. CHI 2020.

#### Other Academic Publications

[1] Burgess, E., Zhang, R., Ernala, S.K., Feuston, J., De Choudhury, M., Schueller, S., Aguilera, A., Czerwinski, M., Reddy, M. (2021). Technology Ecosystems. Rethinking Resources for Mental Health. Interactions Magazine. Forthcoming.

#### PATENTS

- [1] Raravi, G., Kunde, S., Eswaran, S., Chander, D., Rangaswamy, N., Banarjee, J., Ernala, S. K., Radhakrishnan, M., & Sharma, P. Systems and methods for enhancing shopping experience in physical stores, US Patent 10,430,860 (2019)
- [2] Banarjee, J., Raravi, G., Gupta, M., Ernala, S. K., Kunde, S., & Dasgupta, K. Method and system for data processing to recommend list of physical stores in real-time, US Patent App. 15/267,467 (2018).

# INVITED TALKS, PANELS & DEMOS

- CS + Social Good Research Panel. Georgia Tech 2019.
- How well do people report time spent on Facebook? CDS tech talk. Facebook, Inc. 2019.
- Mining online chatter for emerging cyber threats. Cybersecurity lecture series, Georgia Tech. 2019.
- Intersection of social and clinical pathways to care for mental illnesses through social media. ITU Kaleidoscope Conference, Georgia Tech. 2019.
- Intersection of social and clinical pathways to care for mental illnesses through social media. GVU Fall Research Showcase, Georgia Tech. 2019.
- THRIVE: Technology and Health Related Information to Improve Wellness GVU Fall Research Showcase, Georgia Tech. 2018.
- DISCOVER: Generating early warning of cyber threats from online discussions. AI Seminar, Information Sciences Institute, University of Southern California. 2018.
- Examining linguistic markers leading to and following social media disclosures of schizophrenia. GVU Fall Research Showcase, Georgia Tech. 2017.
- Examining behavioral markers leading to social media disclosures on schizophrenia. GVU Fall Research Showcase, Georgia Tech. 2016.

### Selected Press

Facebook Research Blog. Recommendations for researchers to more accurately measure time spent on Facebook. (August, 2020)

TechCrunch. Facebook users are pretty bad at telling how much time they spend on it. (August, 2020)

# SERVICE & SKILLS

**PC Member:** WNUT at EMNLP (2019), The Web Conference (2020, 2021), CHI Late Breaking Work (2020), ICWSM (2019, 2020), ACM WebSci (2020).

#### Reviewing:

Journals Nature Partner Journal (npj) Digital Medicine, PACM CSCW (2018, 2019, 2020), J. Medical Internet Research (JMIR), ACM Transactions on Computer-Human Interaction, ACM Transactions on Computing for Healthcare, IEEE Transactions on Affective Computing, Early Intervention in Psychiatry.

Conferences ICWSM (2019, 2020), CHI (2019\*, 2020), ECIS (2018), The Web Conference (2020, 2021). [\*Special Recognitions for Outstanding Reviews]

#### Mentoring:

Jordyn Seybolt, BS-Psychology Kathan Kashiparekh, MS-CS Amir Girgis, BS-CS Stephanie Yang, BS-CS Tristan Labetoulle, MS-CS Fred Bane, MS-HCI

# Other professional activities/service:

Member, Grad Women @ College of Computing. 2018-2019.

Mentor, I.AM.Grad Computing Workshop in Atlanta. 2019.

Co-organizer, Computational Social Science with Care bi-weekly reading group with inter-university graduate students.

Programming: Python, R, C++, Java, C, SQL, Bash, Presto, Javascript